http://www.marthabuyer.com/articles/2019/12/4/the-california-consumer-privacy-act-comes-of-age.html

Hot Topics
Artificial Intelligence (2) Billing/Excise Tax (1) Broadband Deployment (6) Consumer Issues (41) E-911 (8) Law & Policy (53) Mergers and Acquistions (2) Miscelleanous (3) Mobility (3) Net Neutrality (5) New Technologies (3) Privacy (7) Privacy/data security (8) Spectrum (2) VoIP (2) Wireless (7)
Browse by Date • Publication
ACUTA (2) Buffalo Law Journal (1) Bulletin of the Bar Association of Erie County (14) CCMI (1) Communications Daily (1) Daily Record (1) N (1) No Jitter (78)
August 2020 (1) June 2020 (1) May 2020 (1) February 2020 (1) January 2020 (1) December 2019 (1) November 2019 (2) October 2019 (2) September 2019 (1) August 2019 (1) July 2019 (2) June 2019 (1) April 2019 (1) March 2019 (1) February 2019 (1) January 2019 (1) December 2018 (2) November 2018 (1) October 2018 (1) August 2018 (1) June 2018 (1) May 2018 (2) April 2018 (2) March 2018 (1) January 2018 (3) December 2017 (2) October 2017 (1) September 2017 (1) August 2017 (1) June 2017 (1) May 2017 (2) April 2017 (2) February 2017 (2) December 2016 (1) November 2016 (1) October 2016 (2) July 2016 (1) June 2016 (1) May 2016 (1) February 2016 (2) January 2016 (1) November 2015 (2) October 2015 (1) September 2015 (1) August 2015 (1) June 2015 (3) May 2015 (1) April 2015 (1) February 2015 (2) January 2015 (2) November 2014 (1) October 2014 (1) September 2014 (3) July 2014 (1) June 2014 (1) May 2014 (1) January 2014 (2) December 2013 (2) October 2013 (2) August 2013 (1) April 2013 (2) February 2013 (1) January 2013 (5) October 2012 (2) August 2012 (2) May 2012 (2) April 2012 (2) March 2012 (1) February 2012 (3) January 2012 (2) December 2011 (2) March 2011 (1) February 2011 (1) November 2010 (1) April 2010 (1) February 2010 (1)
Blog Index
Why “Vishing” is the Bad Word of the Week Managing Force Majeure Clauses: Fine Print Does Matter A Short but Important Thank You to Our Vendor Community Creating a Solid Foundation for GDPR, CCPA, Future Laws
AI: It’s All About the Context The California Consumer Privacy Act Comes of Age Data Privacy and 911 Mozilla Case Could Have Ramifications for VoIP Pre-emption VoIP Legality: What Does Federal Inaction Mean? Appeals Court Net Neutrality Review: Mixed Bag
Navigation
Login
WednesdayDec042019
The California Consumer Privacy Act Comes of Age
With
new Californian privacy laws taking effect in the new year, enterprises
are rethinking their strategy and preparing for similar state or
federal regulations.
I’ve written about privacy regulation before. But on January 1, 2020, when the California Consumer Privacy Act takes effect, the importance of managing privacy for California residents and entities will take on a whole new level of seriousness. Aside from some federal obligations contained in HIPAA (Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act, (HIPAA), Financial Credit Reporting Act (FCRA), and the Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act (COPP), for the first time, a state (one may be the loneliest number, but it won’t be the only one for long) will be taking definitive steps to secure the private information of its citizens. The European Union’s rules, called GDPR (General Data Protection Regulation, EU Regulation 2016/679), have been in place since May 2018. While the coverage and approaches are different, there are some useful similarities. This guide from Data Guidance and the Future of Privacy Forum provides a good comparison of the two. However, now that we’re past Thanksgiving, it’s time to start thinking about year-end preparation (of course, after the company holiday party and family fun planning) completed. With the new year quickly approaching, individuals, enterprises, and government officials should all be keenly focused on the obligations and protections of the California Consumer Protection Act (SB-1121) whose obligations may have already been triggered. Since California is thus far the only state to have taken formal action with a firmly committed start date, but as other states step up in this area of great concern to consumers nationwide, implementation and management of the privacy and data protection rules that the new state law require, in some cases, significant steps to protect sensitive information. Visit the California Legislative Information website for the full text of the bill. How to Prepare for CCPAOn the off chance that an enterprise isn’t prepared, what follows are some high-level questions that should be addressed today (better yesterday, but never mind). First, does the CCPA apply to your firm? Is the enterprise selling personal data? If so, and if it’s a for-profit entity that collects California residents’ data, are annual gross revenues over $25 million? Does the enterprise receive personal data of 50,000 individuals, devices, households, or more? Does the enterprise earn 50% or more of its annual revenues from its sale of private consumer data? If any of these three apply, it’s time to get to work on ensuring compliance. Secondly, once you’ve figured out that CCPA does apply, contracts with customers and vendors must be updated to limit liability and provide the necessary notifications to customers. Having a clear understanding of whether or not an entity qualifies as a “service provider” is critical. Once this determination is made, contracts with such entities should clearly address the following circumstances: the business purposes under which the personal information will be processed; a clear prohibition that forbids the service provider from selling the personal information it receives; and a clear prohibition keeping the service provider from retaining, using, or disclosing personal information outside the direct business purpose specified in the contract. (Contracts with third parties who may not qualify as “service providers” should also be updated with respect to personal information, but that’s another topic for another day.) Thirdly, enterprise privacy policies, like bylaws, or any other document designed to manage current corporate circumstances, should be updated regularly. A clear description of what information must be disclosed, as well as what types and frequencies of disclosures, should be understood by those who will be held accountable. This policy should include consumers’ rights to both access and eliminate personal information, as well as its ability to opt out of sales and other unsolicited information. Also, there should be a description of the process for submitting requests of this type, including a website where such requests can be fielded and directed for response. In crafting these policies, which should be modifiable by nature, it’s important that all relevant players are part of the drafting. This should include, at a minimum, attorneys, risk managers, and those responsible for the collection and use of information that is considered private. Time is truly of the essence. For more guidance and information, I recommend this step-by-step guide from The IAPP. While California is the first state where these rules will become effective, other states are likely to follow with similar but not identical provisions. The sooner enterprises can get their collective arms around the key definitions and processes that California requires, the easier it will be when other states—if not the federal government—come to the table with their own rules.
Read the original article in No Jitter here.
Consumer Issues,
| Data Privacy and 911 »
:: PHONE • 716.652.4413 :: FAX • 716.655.9176 :: Copyright © 2012, Martha Buyer, LLC.
All rights reserved.
